A Finding Aid to the Guy Pène Du Bois Papers in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Guy Pène Du Bois papers
circa 1900-1963
bulk 1920-1963
Archives of American Art
Pène Du Bois, Guy, 1884-1958
AAA.duboguyp
Archival Resource Key
2 Linear feet
The papers of painter and art critic Guy Pène Du Bois measure 2.0 linear feet and date from circa 1900 to 1963 with the bulk of the materials dating from 1920 to 1963. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including letters from Royal Cortissoz and Edward Hopper; writings, including essays, journals, short stories, and drafts of the autobiography Artists Say the Silliest Things; personal business records; printed material; and artwork.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sketches and etching proofs were lent to the Archives of American Art in 1970 for microfilming by Pène du Bois' children, Yvonne McKenney and William Pène du Bois. Yvonne McKenney donated papers in 1971. In 1980, two journals dating from 1913 to 1955, were loaned for microfilming by Pène du Bois' daughter-in-law, Willa Kim. These journals were subsequently donated by Martha Fleishman in 2017.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds material lent for microfilming (reel 28) including sketches and etching proofs. Lent material was returned to the lender and is not described in the collection container inventory.
Related Materials
The Archives also holds the Guy Pène Du Bois and Mary Lightfoot Tarleton correspondence.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection and material lent for microfilming are available on 35mm microfilm reels 28-29 and 2008 at the Archives of American Art offices and though interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
Painter and art critic Guy Pène Du Bois (1884-1958) lived and worked in New York City, New York and was known for his realist paintings, essays, and art reviews.
Pène Du Bois was born in Brooklyn, New York to the art critic Henri Pène Du Bois and his wife Laura. After he showed an early interest in art, his' family supported his decision to enroll in William Merritt Chase's New York School of Art at the age of 15. There, Pène Du Bois trained with the realist painters Robert Henri and Kenneth Hayes Miller along with fellow students George Bellows, Edward Hopper, and Rockwell Kent. In 1905, he traveled to Paris and studied briefly with the artist Thèophile Steinlen, but returned to New York the following year after the death of his father. To help support his family, he found work as an illustrator and cartoonist for the New York American, and was promoted to the position of art critic for the newspaper in 1909.
In 1911, Pène Du Bois married his wife, Florence Duncan, and became an assistant writer for the New York Tribune under Royal Cortissoz (1913). Pène Du Bois also wrote art reviews for the New York Post (1916-1918), and was a writer and later editor of Arts and Decoration (1913-1915, 1917-1921). During these years, Pène Du Bois also began to establish a career as a realist painter of note. His work was included in the 1913 Armory Show, after which he signed on as a member of the Kraushaar Gallery stable. Throughout the 1910s, Pène Du Bois exhibited in numerous galleries and museums, and held his first one-man show in 1918 at the Whitney Studio Club.
From 1920 to 1924, Pène Du Bois taught at the Art Students League, and spent the latter part of the 1920s in France with his family. After seven years, he moved his family back to Connecticut and opened the Guy Pène Du Bois School of Art in Stonington, Connecticut. Throughout the 1930s, Pène Du Bois continued painting and received commissions to design federal murals in upstate New York (1937) and Boston (1942). In 1940, Pène Du Bois published his autobiography, Artists Say the Silliest Things. After the death of his wife in 1950, Pène Du Bois lived and traveled with his daughter's family and died in her home in Boston in 1958.
Scope and Contents
The papers of painter and art critic Guy Pène Du Bois measure 2.0 linear feet and date from circa 1900 to 1963 with the bulk of the materials dating from 1920 to 1963. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including letters from Royal Cortissoz and Edward Hopper; writings, including essays, journals, short stories, and drafts of the autobiography Artists Say the Silliest Things; personal business records; printed material; and artwork.
Biographical materials consist of certificates, a curriculum vitae, passport, and a photograph of two unidentified women.
Correspondence is primarily with Pène Du Bois' family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from fellow art critic Royal Cortissoz; artists Raphael Soyer and Edward Hopper; and writers Samuel Duff McCoy, Lincoln Isham, and Newton Booth Tarkington. Other correspondents of note include C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries and Pène Du Bois' son, the children's book illustrator William Pène Du Bois.
Writings include book drafts of Pène Du Bois' autobiography, Artists Say the Silliest Things, journal entries, 35 essays, 8 short stories, and various writing fragments and notes.
Personal business records consist of account and sales records from C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries, book and publishing contracts, and receipts for art supply purchases.
Printed material includes a brochure for the Guy Pène Du Bois School of Art, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and miscellaneous printed material.
Artwork consists of pen and ink sketches by Pène Du Bois and a print by an unknown artist.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Missing Title
Biographical material, 1929-1954 (4 folders; Box 1)
Correspondence, 1908-1958 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Writings, circa 1900-1954 (1.1 linear feet; Box 1-4)
Personal business records, circa 1920-1949 (3 folders; Box 3)
Printed material, circa 1920-1963 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3)
Artwork, circa 1920-1954 (2 folders; Box 3)
Other Finding Aids
Sketches and etching proofs, microfilm reel 29: A list of sketches and proofs is available on the microfilm.
Photographs; Prints; Sketches; Painting, American -- New York (State) -- New York; Art critics -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Cortissoz, Royal, 1869-1948; Hopper, Edward, 1882-1967; McCoy, Samuel Duff, 1882-; Pène du Bois, William, 1916-1993; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987; Tarkington, Booth, 1869-1946; C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries
- Biographical Material, 1929-1954; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials consist of certificates, a curriculum vitae, passport, and a photograph of two unidentified women.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Certificates, 1940-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1935-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Passport, 1929-1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photograph, Two Unidentified Women, circa 1940-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1908-1958; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is primarily with Pène Du Bois' family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from fellow art critic Royal Cortissoz; artists Raphael Soyer and Edward Hopper; and writers Samuel Duff McCoy, Lincoln Isham, and Newton Booth Tarkington. The over 180 letters to Lincoln Isham detail Pène Du Bois' daily life, in addition to covering his thoughts on writing, philosophy, politics, and news of his family.
  Other correspondents of note include C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries and Pène Du Bois' son, the children's book illustrator William Pène Du Bois. There are also letters of condolences addressed to Pène Du Bois' daughter, Yvonne McKenney.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - A Miscellaneous, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Artists Group Inc., 1939-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - B Miscellaneous, 1929-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bartlett, Clay, 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C Miscellaneous, 1936-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1937-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cooper Union, 1942-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cortissoz, Royal, 1930-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries, 1940-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - D Miscellaneous, 1940-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Du Bois, George, 1951-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Du Bois, Guy Pène, 1941-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Du Bois, William Pène, 1944-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Du Bois, William Pène and Jane, 1950-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Du Bois, William Pène and Willa, 1953-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Duncan, Rita Jean, 1950-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Duncan, Robert, 1949-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - E-H Miscellaneous, 1939-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hopper, Edward, 1931-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - I Miscellaneous, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Isham, Lincoln and Lea, 1942-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - J-M Miscellaneous, 1908-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Macy, George, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - McCoy, Samuel Duff and Neely, 1949-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Merritt, Nancy Lucas, 1951-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - N-P Miscellaneous, 1939-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Q-S Miscellaneous, 1939-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Soyer, Raphael, 1951-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - T Miscellaneous, 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Tarkington, Newton Booth, 1943-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - U Miscellaneous, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - U.S. Treasury Department, 1936-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - V-W Miscellaneous, 1940-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Watson, Forbes, 1932-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - X-Z Miscellaneous, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Unknown and Illegible, circa 1940-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Condolences, A-Z, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
- Writings, circa 1900-1954; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Box 1-4
  Writings include book drafts of Pène Du Bois' autobiography, Artists Say the Silliest Things, 2 bound journals dating from 1913-1955, journal entries, 35 essays on various art related topics, 8 short stories, and various writing fragments and notes. The journal entries are primarily writing exercises in essay style and cover diverse topics of fashion, character studies, art history, and current events.
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part One, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part One (copy 1, incomplete), circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part One (fragments), circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part One (handwritten draft, incomplete), circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part Two, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part Two (copy 1), circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part Two (copy 2, incomplete), circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part Two (handwritten draft), circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Book, Untitled, Chapters 1-2, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Book Proposals, circa 1940-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Book Reviews, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Essay, "Apes and Angels in Art", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Essay, "Art and Decoration", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Essay, "Art and the Decline of the Bourgeoise", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Essay, "Art is Art and Life is Life", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Essay, "Children's Books", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Essay, "Classicism", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Essay, "Clothes and War and Art", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Essay, "Contrasts and Contemporaneous Art", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Essay, "Decoration", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Essay, "Eclectics", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Essay, "Disordered Notes of an Ex Art Critic", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Essay, "Essay Written for an American", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Essay, "Eyes are Windows", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Essay, "Forbears of the Fashionable Linguists", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Essay, "High Art and Hillbillies", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Essay, "Holley and the Square", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Essay, "Note on Fashion", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Essay, "Note on Modern Art", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Essay, "Note on Statues", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Essay, "Note on the American Scene Painting", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Essay, "On the Satirist", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Essay, On Artists and World Affairs, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Essay, On Children's Book Fair, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Essay, On Denys Wortman, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Essay, On French Modernism, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Essay, On Intellectualism, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Essay, On Seeing Art, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Essay, On Space, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Essay, On Style and Fashion, circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Essay, "Realism", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Essay, "Romanticism", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Essay, "Seeing Could Be Believing", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Essay, "Seeing in Its Relation to the Visual Arts", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Essay, "Turnabout in Art", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Essay, "War and Art", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Journal Entries, 1949-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Journal, 1913-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
  - Journal, 1926-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
  - Stories, "1907 New York," "Question of Bravery," "Sailors," "The Square", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Story, "Final Flourish", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Story, "Over-Lord", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Story, "Staten Island", circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Story, "Wild Horses in Harlem", circa 1930-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Fragments, Handwritten, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Fragments, Typescripts, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Fragments, Introductions, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fragments, Stories, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notes, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Letters of Frederick von Elder," by Unknown Author, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Moral Freedom--Natural Law," by W.W. Sherman, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1920-1949; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 3
  Personal business records consist of account and sales records from C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries, two book and publishing contracts, and miscellaneous receipts for art supply purchases.
  - Account Records, C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries, 1937-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Contracts, 1930-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Receipts, circa 1920-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Printed Material, circa 1920-1963; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3
  Printed material includes a brochure for the Guy Pène Du Bois School of Art, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Brochure, Guy Pène Du Bois School of Art, 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, circa 1920-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Clippings, 1920-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14-18)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1954-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, Other Artists, 1942-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Periodical, Magazine of Art, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1931-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Artwork, circa 1920-1954; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 3
  Artwork consists of pen and ink sketches by Pène Du Bois and a print by an unknown artist.
  Materials are arranged by artist.
  - Sketches, circa 1920-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Artwork by Others, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)